A few years ago, a computing
lecturer accidentally discovered
a sorting algorithm in that they were lecturing
and they're like, "Oh, here's an example of some
pseudo code that doesn't sort." And I don't know
how they found out, maybe a student was like, "Uh
uh that works." And it did. It actually worked
as a sorting algorithm, not just sort of just
sort. I mean, it turns out code, just like
everything evolves to become a crab, all code
becomes a sorting algorithm. And uh we're going to
we're going to have a closer look at it. [music]
[music]
First things first, as is the theme today, what
is a sorting algorithm? Well, here I have some
squares in the wrong order. I always want these to
go from smallest to biggest, your left to right.
And as a human, I'd be like, "Well, there's the
smallest one, so I'm going to pull that one out,
swap it with the one which is where it should be."
And then I'll look and go, "Uh there's the next
smallest." And what I'm doing, cuz I'm always
selecting the next one that needs to be moved
up the list, this is just called selection sort.
And what I'm doing here, ah done. What I'm doing
here is just finding, each time I scan the whole
list, find the next one that's in the wrong place,
move it up to where it should be. And that kind
of gives us the two different aspects to sorting
algorithms. There's the actual logic behind what
you're doing, and then separately, and some would
say more importantly, how would you code that up
so a computer can do it automatically. Fun fact,
I made these opening titles that you saw a moment
ago using selection sort. I scrambled it into 120
vertical strips and then sorted them back into
order. It's a nice way to visualize it. So,
here are four more. Now, these aren't all the
same speed. I've had to speed up cocktail shaker
and insertion so that it's done in the time
available, whereas quick sort, look at that,
it's actually done. It's just that quick. And
merge sort, oh my goodness, love merge sort.
That's also going at the same steady pace. But I
want to speed it up because you can see kind of
like how it's working. Look, it's making low-res
versions of me and then merging them all together.
Ah, it's great. We'll get to some actual sorting
algorithms in a moment, ridiculous and otherwise.
But you might be thinking, why do I have to care
about sorting algorithms? Like computers do that
for me. And that's one of the reasons. Computers
have got a sort. Like the moment you start writing
code, you're going to need a sorting algorithm,
be it like for data processing or even like like
now. If you want to sort the comments under this
video by most recent because you're some kind of
monster. You can do that and there's some
code in the background running a sorting
algorithm. So it's an unavoidable part of
writing code. But you think, well, hang on,
it's already been solved. I just import sort
thing. Well, thinking through the logic of how
a sorting algorithm works is a really nice way to
just teach your brain how to understand, follow,
and use algorithms. So in terms of a learning
tool, highly recommend it. Probably be why there
was a lecture on it which caused this whole thing
to start. And job interviews, like if you want
to become a software developer, this is a classic
question to have to write out some pseudo code for
different sorting algorithms. And finally, it's
fun. I like it. Recreational sorting algorithms,
I think I think they're great. So I'm on board.
So there's my four reasons. And at the moment
in the wrong order, so I'll just sort them into
order I care about. There you are. They're fun.
And I don't want I don't want to risk getting a
job. Okay, the first algorithm we're going to look
at is a classic of the genre, bubble sort. This
is the sorting algorithm that it seems everybody
knows, but also everybody hates. What is the most
efficient way to sort a million 32-bit integers?
Well, uh I'm I'm maybe I'm I'm sorry. Maybe
we should No, no, no, no, no. I I I think
I I I think I think the the bubble sort would
be the wrong way to go. But before we get to the
exact details of stepping through bubble sort,
it occurs to me some of you may want a job.
I mean, as a software developer or turns out
president. And in that case, you're going to
love the sponsor of today's video, boot.dev. It is
a fantastic, interactive, and indeed addictive way
to learn modern software developer skills.
I mean, we're talking Python, SQL, Go,
other languages. Check out all these courses I
can do. I'm so excited. Now, a bunch of you are
thinking, "Obviously, Matt, you're a terrible
Python coder. You're going to learn Python for
beginners. Come on, get in there." But no, you'd
be wrong. Going to go back. I'm going to learn
Git. Oh, look, the name is the primogen. Huh.
Right, so here we go. I'm going to do this, and
you'll never be able to mock my version control
again. All the content on boot.dev is free for you
to read and watch. So, you've got no excuses.
And if you do get a paid membership, 25% off
if you use my code, that means you access all the
interactive elements. We've got hands-on coding,
AI assistance, progress tracking, and game
mechanics. That's a good deal. So, if you
want to learn to code or just improve your skills,
join me at boot.dev. Discount code standupmaths.
Come on this adventure together. Thanks to
boot.dev for sponsoring this video. And if
you use the QR code on screen right now or the
link in the description, you can get 25% off
your first annual membership. Learn coding.
Learn how to do things like putting ridiculous
pi symbols in QR codes automatically. Uh on which
I have no further comment. Thanks, boot.dev. Now,
I think these are probably randomized enough.
Let's talk bubble sort. To do our bubble sort,
we're going to start with a counter I over here
at index zero. So, because this is computing,
we're going to go position zero, 1 2 3 4, and all
we do is look at position I compared to I + 1,
and if they're in the wrong order, we swap
them. If they're not, we don't. And so,
the first two are in the wrong order, so I swap
those. Here we are, cuz now it goes smaller
bigger. Then we compare the next two. They're
in the wrong order, so we swap them. Smaller
bigger. And you may notice, because this is
like the second biggest and a smaller bigger,
it's going to bubble all the way up until it
gets here. Now, these are in the right order,
so we go back to the beginning again. Next pass,
the first two are already in the right order.
The next two are in the wrong order, so we swap
those, and then everything else is correct,
and then we go back over. They're in the wrong
order, so we swap them, and everything else
is correct. And as soon as we can do a complete
pass comparing every pair and they're all right,
we know we are finished. That is bubble sort.
That felt like fun. It didn't take that long.
So, you know what? Let's Let's see if we can
put it together in some pseudo code. N minus
two. Okay, so I've done for I equals zero, which
means it starts there in the zeroth position,
to N minus two. This will be the N minus one
position, that's the N minus two position.
We want to stop one short, because then
we take uh if I is greater than I + 1.
Because here, we always compare I
to I + 1, so I has to stop here,
so we have an I + 1 to compare it to. That's
the final pair. And if I is greater than I + 1,
which means they're the wrong way around,
cuz we want them smaller to bigger,
I'm just saying here, take the list position
I and list position I plus one and swap them.
So, that becomes equal to that and that becomes
equal to that. Although, oh wait, we need to stop
once we do a complete pass and nothing
changes. So, what you'll probably do
All right, this is not great, but I've put a
bit of extra room at the beginning there. So,
each time it goes through iterates through this,
it resets finished to true, but then if it has to
do a swap, it changes finished to false. And if
it happens to get through all of these without a
single flipping to false, it'll hit the end and if
finished, so if it's true, it'll return the list.
But if finished is false, it'll go back up again.
So, this way it'll iterate through this over and
over and over again until one time it doesn't do
any swaps, finished stays true, and it ends. So,
there you are. Uh terrible pseudo code for bubble
sort. And if you are thinking, well, you know
what? It's not that bad, pretty simple code, very
straightforward algorithm. We sorted these pretty
quickly. It's very inefficient for bigger and
bigger lists of data because you have to go you
have to scan like if you've got to move one from
one end to the other end, you have to scan the
entire list that many times. And so, while it's
lovely as an example, in practice, it is awful.
Thanks, Obama. Okay, let me show you what
the lecturer, uh someone named Stanley Fung,
actually did when they were trying to set
up some pseudo code that would not sort.
All right, there it is. That's the entirety of the
pseudo code that Stanley wrote up on the board.
And they were just making up something that wasn't
going to work. And look how ridiculous this is.
For equals zero to n minus one, so the the
first counter just points at every single
item in the list in order. And for each
of those, J then points at every single
item in the list in order. And then to cap it
all off, as well as the ridiculous iteration,
we always check if if this is correct. So we
want I to be smaller than J. If they're right,
break it. So only if they're in the correct order
already, you swap them the other way around.
And if they're in the wrong order, you leave them
alone. And it works. Uh spoiler, um it's because
this ridiculousness accidentally cancels with this
ridiculousness because I and J swap sides. But you
know what we're going to do? Well, actually we'll
step through this and you can see it for yourself.
Okay, here we go. This is so stupid, I love
it. So uh first counter I starts over here at
position zero. J also zero. We compare this to
itself because there are no efficiencies here
and uh it's not smaller than itself, so it gets
to stay. Okay, next step. We now compare this to
all of them. So we compare it to this one. They're
in the wrong order. They're descending, which is
incorrect, so we leave them. We compare these two.
Oh, they're the right order. Okay, let's fix that.
Please. There we go. Now we continue to compare
this position. So uh they're in the wrong order,
they're in the wrong order. First pass complete
and you may have noticed what it's done
is it's taken the biggest item and moved it to
the zeroth position, the beginning of the list,
and it will always do that. So remember that.
Okay, second pass. Now you're going to watch
this real close because this is now position I,
but J still starts at the beginning. And actually
we're looking at them from the other side now
because J is before I. So when we compare these,
we're actually comparing them in the reverse
direction and they are in the right order from
the wrong direction, so we swap them. And so,
these two swap. Now, we compare that to itself.
All good. And we carry on kind of like before.
These are in the wrong order, so they stay.
Wrong order, they stay. Wrong order, they stay.
Okay, next pass. I is now here. We're looking
the wrong way, and they are in the wrong order,
so they stay. They're in They're in the right
order from the wrong direction, so they swap.
Yes, okay, I got this. That stays where it is.
These are in the wrong order, so they
stay. Wrong order, so they stay. [sighs]
Two to go. So, we're here. This is our I. J starts
way over there again. So, we're looking in the
wrong order, but they're in the wrong order, so
they Oh, they stay. That's the correct order, but
the wrong way around, so they have to swap. Now,
we're looking at these. And they have to swap.
That compared to itself, and then these are in
the wrong order, so they stay. Oh, last. How is
this going to work? Last pass. This one compared
to the very beginning one are in the wrong order,
so they stay. Oh, that's why it works. Wrong
order, so they stay. The correct order from
the wrong way around, so they swap. And then we
compare this. They're in the the wrong direction,
the wrong, but that cancels, and so they swap.
And then we compare that to itself, and it did it.
Oh, I can't believe it works. I can't
believe it sorts. God, I love it so much.
That makes me so angry. That's art. Okay, we all
just took a moment here to collect ourselves,
and we're okay now. It's so ridiculous, but you
may have noticed how it works. So, it always takes
the biggest one, chucks it to the wrong end,
and then drags it all the way up, uh kind of
plowing through the list. And behind it, it leaves
things in the correct order. And that's because
on the actual business side of the sort, behind
the biggest one, J's always on the other side.
And so, because of they're flipped, doing
it the wrong way is doing it the right way,
and they all end up perfectly in order. Although,
a fun side effect, if you start with the list
already sorted, which things like bubble sort
would just leave alone and be like, "Yep, done."
I can't believe it can sort will always take the
biggest one, put it there, and drag it up. So,
you've got to go through the whole process every
time, even if it starts sorted. In that regard,
a terrible algorithm. But, the reason I think it's
a great algorithm is because it is so surprising,
and you've really got to think it through. In that
regard, excellent example for teaching algorithmic
thinking, which is why, when Stanley Fong stumbled
across this trying to come up with the algorithm
that didn't sort, they wrote a whole paper about
it. They named it I Can't Believe It Can Sort.
And it's a great paper. I'll link to it below
if you want to go check it out. Stanley proves
why this works. Although, when they're proof,
they use index one, so just bear that in mind
when you see the proof. Lovely paper. I actually
contacted Stanley at the time, back in 2021, had
a chat about it. And Stanley did point out some
people were taking the paper a little seriously,
and they have a whole addendum where they're
answering some of the common questions and
comments and critiques, because Stanley's not
claiming no one else ever did this before them.
They just are the first person who documented it
and realized how counterintuitive it is. And I'm
glad they did it. And you know, I'm prepared to
declare that I Can't Believe It Can Sort is my
official favorite sorting algorithm. Just over 10
years ago, there was this incredible video that
did an incredible sonification and visualization
of 15 different sorting algorithms in 6 minutes.
I'll link to it below if you want to check it
out. You should. Oh, this This is bubble sort. So,
you really get a sense cuz you can see which ones
are being compared and how it's being processed
how the sorting algorithm actually works.
Ah, that's This really nice. And here we go.
Sorted. Now, I'm not going to try and
recreate their fantastic sonification,
but I thought I would take a
very large list of random numbers
and I'd do the equivalent visualization for
I can't believe it can sort. Here you go.
Turns out that Past Mat is a liar. I realized that
Timo Bingmann, who made that video back in 2013,
put all their code open source on GitHub.
So, I was able to just get a copy of that,
clip on I Can't Believe It Can Sort, the latest
and greatest sorting algorithm, and render out
the visualization that you're looking at now. But,
let me be clear. What you're enjoying now is still
100% Timo's excellent creative work, now with a
twist of Stanley's terrible sorting algorithm.
If you do watch that original video, you will
realize there's so many different sorting
algorithms out there. They all have pros and
cons, features, things they do and don't do.
Some edit the list in place. Some duplicate
the list and then mess with that. Merge sort
splits the list into smaller and smaller lists.
And then when it recombines them all, the items
end up in the correct order. And merge sort is
kind of practical. If you're wondering
what is actually used, Python used to use
something called Tim sort. And it's called Tim
sort because it was named after a guy called Tim.
Tim Peters invented it. And it's kind of a hybrid
sort. It does use merge sort, but also use like
insertion sort. Cuz what it's doing is looking for
sub sections of the data which are already sorted
and then capitalizes on that. Because some
algorithms are good for data that's completely
random, some are good if it's already basically
sorted and a few are just in the wrong place, some
are good for long lists, some are good for short
lists. So, your actual libraries, if you import
a sort method, will probably use a combination
of different methods based on the data you're
putting into it. And Python now, Python 3, uses
power sort, which sorts uh powerfully. Um yeah.
Look it up yourself. All jokes aside, because
that was technically a joke, you've got at the
extreme practical end now power sort. That's what
Python 3 uses. At the other end of the useful to
ridiculous spectrum, you've got things like uh
uh bogo sort. That's where you just randomly
keep shuffling the list until it's actually
sorted. And you've got things like Thanos sort,
where you just randomly delete half the items in
the list until whatever's left is in the order
you want. And in the middle, you've got I can't
believe it can sort, because it is ridiculous,
but it works. And it wasn't like deliberately
designed to be a ridiculous sorting algorithm,
like some of the more esoteric ones, but it
wasn't even designed to work, but it does. Ah,
which is why I love it so much. If you want
to learn more about the sorting algorithms,
I'm going to link to actually a video by boot.dev.
It's really good. I came across it after I'd
already asked them to sponsor this video. Pure
coincidence. Nice video, link below. Don't forget,
25% off a one-year plan if you use my ridiculous
QR code link in the description and that's it.
Have fun with your sorting algorithms and
if you've got a favorite sorting algorithm,
put it in the comments below. I'll sort
I'll sort by best sorting algorithm.
All right, I'll randomize them cuz I want to show
you sleep sort. This is where you assign a delay
for each one. This is quite small, 1 second. Each
delay is weighted, that's quite big, 5 seconds,
by how big it is. And if you assign a bunch of
delays, sleeps, they'll all then pop back up
again. They'll print to the screen in the order
that they're sized. Sleep sort. Ridiculous.